يَوْمَ تَكُونُ السَّمَاءُ كَالْمُهْلِ - 70:8 وَتَكُونُ الْجِبَالُ كَالْعِهْنِ - 70:9
On the Day the sky will be like murky oil, and the mountains will be like wool,
وَلَا يَسْأَلُ حَمِيمٌ حَمِيمًا - 70:10
And no friend will ask [anything of] a friend,
يُبَصَّرُونَهُمْ ۚ يَوَدُّ الْمُجْرِمُ لَوْ يَفْتَدِي مِنْ عَذَابِ يَوْمِئِذٍ بِبَنِيهِ - 70:11
They will be shown each other. The criminal will wish that he could be ransomed from the punishment of that Day by his children
وَصَاحِبَتِهِ وَأَخِيهِ - 70:12
And his wife and his brother
وَفَصِيلَتِهِ الَّتِي تُؤْوِيهِ - 70:13
And his nearest kindred who shelter him
وَمَن فِي الْأَرْضِ جَمِيعًا ثُمَّ يُنجِيهِ - 70:14
And whoever is on earth entirely [so] then it could save him.
كَلَّا ۖ إِنَّهَا لَظَىٰ - 70:15 نَزَّاعَةً لِّلشَّوَىٰ - 70:16 تَدْعُو مَنْ أَدْبَرَ وَتَوَلَّىٰ - 70:17
No! Indeed, it is the Flame [of Hell], a remover of exteriors. It invites he who turned his back [on truth] and went away [from obedience]
وَجَمَعَ فَأَوْعَىٰ - 70:18
And collected [wealth] and hoarded.
إِنَّ الْإِنسَانَ خُلِقَ هَلُوعًا - 70:19 إِذَا مَسَّهُ الشَّرُّ جَزُوعًا - 70:20
Indeed, mankind was created anxious: when evil touches him, impatient,
وَإِذَا مَسَّهُ الْخَيْرُ مَنُوعًا - 70:21
And when good touches him, withholding [of it],
أعوذ بالله من الشيطان الرجيم
I seek refuge in Allah from the cursed Satan
بسم الله الرحمن الرحيم
In the name of Allah, The All-Merciful, The Ever-Merciful
سَأَلَ سَائِلٌ بِعَذَابٍ وَاقِعٍ - 70:1
A supplicant asked for a punishment bound to happen
لِّلْكَافِرِينَ لَيْسَ لَهُ دَافِعٌ - 70:2 مِّنَ اللَّهِ ذِي الْمَعَارِجِ - 70:3
To the disbelievers; of it there is no preventer. [It is] from Allah, owner of the ways of ascent.
تَعْرُجُ الْمَلَائِكَةُ وَالرُّوحُ إِلَيْهِ فِي يَوْمٍ كَانَ مِقْدَارُهُ خَمْسِينَ أَلْفَ سَنَةٍ - 70:4
The angels and the Spirit will ascend to Him during a Day the extent of which is fifty thousand years.
فَاصْبِرْ صَبْرًا جَمِيلًا - 70:5 إِنَّهُمْ يَرَوْنَهُ بَعِيدًا - 70:6 وَنَرَاهُ قَرِيبًا - 70:7
So be patient with gracious patience. Indeed, they see it [as] distant, but We see it [as] near.
يَوْمَ تَكُونُ السَّمَاءُ كَالْمُهْلِ - 70:8 وَتَكُونُ الْجِبَالُ كَالْعِهْنِ - 70:9
On the Day the sky will be like murky oil, and the mountains will be like wool,
وَلَا يَسْأَلُ حَمِيمٌ حَمِيمًا - 70:10
And no friend will ask [anything of] a friend,
يُبَصَّرُونَهُمْ ۚ يَوَدُّ الْمُجْرِمُ لَوْ يَفْتَدِي مِنْ عَذَابِ يَوْمِئِذٍ بِبَنِيهِ - 70:11
They will be shown each other. The criminal will wish that he could be ransomed from the punishment of that Day by his children
وَصَاحِبَتِهِ وَأَخِيهِ - 70:12
And his wife and his brother
وَفَصِيلَتِهِ الَّتِي تُؤْوِيهِ - 70:13
And his nearest kindred who shelter him
وَمَن فِي الْأَرْضِ جَمِيعًا ثُمَّ يُنجِيهِ - 70:14
And whoever is on earth entirely [so] then it could save him.
كَلَّا ۖ إِنَّهَا لَظَىٰ - 70:15 نَزَّاعَةً لِّلشَّوَىٰ - 70:16 تَدْعُو مَنْ أَدْبَرَ وَتَوَلَّىٰ - 70:17
No! Indeed, it is the Flame [of Hell], a remover of exteriors. It invites he who turned his back [on truth] and went away [from obedience]
وَجَمَعَ فَأَوْعَىٰ - 70:18
And collected [wealth] and hoarded.
إِنَّ الْإِنسَانَ خُلِقَ هَلُوعًا - 70:19 إِذَا مَسَّهُ الشَّرُّ جَزُوعًا - 70:20
Indeed, mankind was created anxious: when evil touches him, impatient,
وَإِذَا مَسَّهُ الْخَيْرُ مَنُوعًا - 70:21
And when good touches him, withholding [of it],
إِلَّا الْمُصَلِّينَ - 70:22 الَّذِينَ هُمْ عَلَىٰ صَلَاتِهِمْ دَائِمُونَ - 70:23 وَالَّذِينَ فِي أَمْوَالِهِمْ حَقٌّ مَّعْلُومٌ - 70:24
Except the observers of prayer - those who are constant in their prayer and those within whose wealth is a known right.
لِّلسَّائِلِ وَالْمَحْرُومِ - 70:25 وَالَّذِينَ يُصَدِّقُونَ بِيَوْمِ الدِّينِ - 70:26
For the petitioner and the deprived - and those who believe in the Day of Recompense
وَالَّذِينَ هُم مِّنْ عَذَابِ رَبِّهِم مُّشْفِقُونَ - 70:27 إِنَّ عَذَابَ رَبِّهِمْ غَيْرُ مَأْمُونٍ - 70:28
And those who are fearful of the punishment of their Lord - indeed, the punishment of their Lord is not that from which one is safe -
وَالَّذِينَ هُمْ لِفُرُوجِهِمْ حَافِظُونَ-70:29 إِلَّا عَلَىٰ أَزْوَاجِهِمْ أَوْ مَا مَلَكَتْ أَيْمَانُهُمْ فَإِنَّهُمْ غَيْرُ مَلُومِينَ-70:30
And those who guard their private parts except from their wives or those their right hands possess, for indeed, they are not to be blamed
فَمَنِ ابْتَغَىٰ وَرَاءَ ذَٰلِكَ فَأُولَٰئِكَ هُمُ الْعَادُونَ - 70:31
But whoever seeks beyond that, then they are the transgressors -
وَالَّذِينَ هُمْ لِأَمَانَاتِهِمْ وَعَهْدِهِمْ رَاعُونَ - 70:32
And those who are to their trusts and promises attentive
وَالَّذِينَ هُم بِشَهَادَاتِهِمْ قَائِمُونَ - 70:33 وَالَّذِينَ هُمْ عَلَىٰ صَلَاتِهِمْ يُحَافِظُونَ - 70:34
And those who are in their testimonies upright and those who [carefully] maintain their prayer:
أُولَٰئِكَ فِي جَنَّاتٍ مُّكْرَمُونَ - 70:35 فَمَالِ الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا قِبَلَكَ مُهْطِعِينَ - 70:36
They will be in gardens, honored. So what is [the matter] with those who disbelieve, hastening [from] before you, [O Muhammad],
عَنِ الْيَمِينِ وَعَنِ الشِّمَالِ عِزِينَ - 70:37
[To sit] on [your] right and [your] left in separate groups?
أَيَطْمَعُ كُلُّ امْرِئٍ مِّنْهُمْ أَن يُدْخَلَ جَنَّةَ نَعِيمٍ - 70:38
Does every person among them aspire to enter a garden of pleasure?
كَلَّا ۖ إِنَّا خَلَقْنَاهُم مِّمَّا يَعْلَمُونَ - 70:39
No! Indeed, We have created them from that which they know.
فَلَا أُقْسِمُ بِرَبِّ الْمَشَارِقِ وَالْمَغَارِبِ إِنَّا لَقَادِرُونَ - 70:40
So I swear by the Lord of [all] risings and settings that indeed We are able
عَلَىٰ أَن نُّبَدِّلَ خَيْرًا مِّنْهُمْ وَمَا نَحْنُ بِمَسْبُوقِينَ - 70:41
To replace them with better than them; and We are not to be outdone.
فَذَرْهُمْ يَخُوضُوا وَيَلْعَبُوا حَتَّىٰ يُلَاقُوا يَوْمَهُمُ الَّذِي يُوعَدُونَ - 70:42
So leave them to converse vainly and amuse themselves until they meet their Day which they are promised -
يَوْمَ يَخْرُجُونَ مِنَ الْأَجْدَاثِ سِرَاعًا كَأَنَّهُمْ إِلَىٰ نُصُبٍ يُوفِضُونَ - 70:43
The Day they will emerge from the graves rapidly as if they were, toward an erected idol, hastening.
خَاشِعَةً أَبْصَارُهُمْ تَرْهَقُهُمْ ذِلَّةٌ ۚ ذَٰلِكَ الْيَوْمُ الَّذِي كَانُوا يُوعَدُونَ - 70:44
Their eyes humbled, humiliation will cover them. That is the Day which they had been promised.